e
so I can the introduction switch over
whatever this is functioning as a
let's move it
over
e e
so I think we're about ready to get
started so uh everybody do me a favor
cross your fingers real real quick and
that the zoom gods and HDMI key Gods all
work for us because we're running a zoom
session between two laptops here to make
this project up there to get recorded to
go to another Zoom online for all the
online viewers so fingers crossed right
this what so all right so terrific uh so
uh user Behavior insights is this talk
uh formally titled your search engine
needs a memory um and so I am going to
do
some I am G to do some introductions so
uh yeah intentionally blank slide so uh
my name is Eric Pew um for those of you
um I'm one of the co-founders of osc and
maybe more relevant to this crowd I'm
actually one of the instigators of
haystack something that I'm inordinately
proud about and more proud every year
seeing this amazing turnout so yeah so
that's me um and uh this uh this this
talk uh is based on uh a presentation um
a couple of years ago say September 29th
2021 uh when Trey Max and Doug gave a
panel uh either gave a panel discussion
about AI powered search or I was reading
an early uh maning Early Access access
version of their book and in AI power
search they talked a lot about
generalizable signals format and
collecting signals so I opened this
issue in one of our open source repos
wouldn't it be cool to track clicks
using a generalizable signals format so
uh that was uh my interest in this you
know obviously dates back a couple years
so really excited to be here now uh
co-presenting with me is stavos so for
those of you uh who don't know stabos
has got deep expertise uh in the search
field background at Leos and Google and
a couple of other bigname companies and
done a lot of interesting things and
today he is a senior technical product
manager for open search uh at
AWS um stabos you know definitely has a
certain type of
humor and I looked at my email and I
enjoyed finding my first inter
interaction with stabos uh and I think
this is a classic stabos email very to
the point very short uh but I'm learning
to appreciate them so I I it was kind of
really just wonderful to be like wow
you've been involved in the hyack
community for a while and I do remember
getting this email a long time ago and
saying wow there's this there's real
interest in this conference so little
bit of a trip down memory lane uh that
you all could do with me so uh yeah so
we're really excited here to be talking
about user Behavior insights I'm going
to hand it over to stavos to set a
little bit of context and then I'm going
to do a demo everything working out uh
and show maybe some of the more
technical bits of the work that we've
been doing so all right so let's do a
quick handoff
that was a lot of
words so I'm G to talk a little bit
about why we need
oh why we need user Behavior insights uh
and Eric's actually going to do the hard
part of the work
here um I think we all know I hope we
all know that search needs
data we need to know what's going on out
there it's not enough we have of course
have the Corpus data but I'm not talking
about the Corp data we need data about
how people are using search what do we
need it for well I'd like to go back to
a basic difference in our field between
databases and search in databases you
write your SQL query and you know
exactly what should come out it's well-
defined there's no question of is it a
good result or a bad result may not be
the result you wanted but it what is a
correct result for the SQL query is well
defined that's not true of course in
search in search you want the best
results and typically there are many too
many results to show all of them so you
can't say oh yes we're going to show all
the results and the user can choose the
best ones we know this I mean this is
not not this is not rocket science here
but what do you want to know you want to
know are the results good did we show
the good results um and what's good you
want to know which are the best
results how do you know which are the
best ones so that's one reason you want
data another reason you want data is you
want to adapt your results to the Corpus
that is the collection of documents you
have and to the user population and this
slide obviously not going to go this
through this in detail but the idea here
is that if you look at this slide there
are huge numbers of applications of
search and we've heard about this at the
conference today and yesterday uh huge
numbers of applications and each of them
has a different notion of relevance
there's not a universal notion of
relevance so how do you know where
whether a document is relevant you look
at how people interact with
it so I would claim that the unifying
concept behind search is relevance
ranking SQL is is fine as far as it goes
doesn't have the concept of relevance
ranking sometimes people say oh we'll
just use SQL to do to do search and if
you have some sort of heuristic about uh
what is relevant and what isn't you can
actually do a pretty good job in fact um
a few years ago I had to do a company
search uh for which is like a subsidiary
search within a bigger
application and we had you know hundreds
of thousands of companies in our Corpus
but we knew that large companies are of
more interest to our users than small
companies we knew that companies that
they had worked on before were more
interesting than companies that they
hadn't worked on before and of course
the data was dirty sometimes the largest
companies actually weren't even listed
as large companies and so on so you had
to have some sort of notion of dealing
with dirty data and so what did I do I I
went to my machine learning uh colleague
and said here's this Corpus of data and
let's let's figure out how we can uh
adjust the the weights on different
factors no that's not what I did what I
did was I used uh I think Trey likes
this tool too um I used my wet finger
put it in the air and said okay I think
the size of the company is probably
really important and the address is
probably not important at all I'm not
going to use that and this and that so I
had about 10 factors and I put them in
and adjusted the factors and got H not
so great results I said okay well let's
make this one logarithmic let's make
this one a bigger Factor smaller factor
and sure enough you know damn thing
actually worked really well I deployed
it actually I didn't we didn't deploy
the SQL version We I went to my
engineers and said here's a SQL
prototype do it and and it worked
beautifully so actually SQL is a great
tool if you know how to to rank
things but again I'd say that search is
relevance ranking and usually you can't
do something as simple as what I did you
can't say oh yes the you know a lexical
search in the description is worth half
as much as a lexical search in the title
or whatever you know all that sort of
thing so what's our goal with user
Behavior insights our goal is to collect
all the information you need for
evaluating search based on user
Behavior now why is that hard uh you
think well I can go to uh large company
X analytics or large company y analytics
and buy their solution and gives me the
information I need well most of the
analytic Solutions on the market are
about aggregate data they're about
telling you what proportion of the users
use this page how often did they hit the
back button you know things like
this there are as far as I know there
are no good solutions for us the search
community that are especially not
available in open source I mean I
suspect there are some uh that are
proprietary to some of the other vendors
but not something that's available in
open source not something that could be
used by anyone and in fact one thing
that I should probably mention now is
that our solution is not linked to open
search the product or open search the
codebase can be used with any search
system and we'd like to make it usable
for
everyone so what kinds of questions do
we want to ask when we evaluating search
you want to say what did they use the
what do they search for okay that's an
easy one usually you can log the
searches that's that's not so hard how
did they use typ ahead okay can probably
do that how do they refine the search
what's the SE sequence of facets they
used which facets did they hit first
which did they hit second how much did
that reduce the uh the result list each
time getting a little harder to to do
using standard analytics
techniques what search or SE oops
sorry uh what search or sequence of
searches led to a particular purchase so
if I'm the category manager for slippers
and I want to know red slipper number
235 how do people find it are they
searching for red slippers are they
searching for warm slippers what what
exactly are they searching for so you
can search backwards and say starting
with the thing that was bought how did
they end up buying it how did they they
find it and that may involve not only
the sequence of events after the search
it may involve the sequence of events
before the search so they may have done
previous searches they may have looked
at recommendations you want to see what
the user was exposed to before they did
the search
and of course you know you want all the
actions I mean that's that's the sort of
the obvious part you want to know they
clicked on this they hovered over on
that uh they uh they hit the back button
uh you know all that kind of thing and
said that's a lot of data and say it's
2024 guy you know uh uh the famous uh
Google uh uh video where someone says I
want to serve uh 5 terabytes and the
answer from this uh system relevant the
system of reliability Engineers I can't
remember how to count that low
anymore so you know these days the data
volume is not an issue and we have a lot
of experience at open search certainly
but also all our competitors have
experience with very very voluminous log
data so the
infrastructure I got a popup auto update
what is outut update here oh thank you
Amon um these things happen at least
once a week by the way um
so um yes so what was I saying
um all right so we know that we want to
collect lots of
data and say well maybe people are
already collecting this data Maybe may
maybe this's a salt problem so my boss
Eli and I two years ago at Berlin
buzzwords where we there was an
unconference and so we got a bunch of
people about about as many as they're in
this this room
today and we asked them what are the
important things that every search
implementation should
do okay so we did you know the usual
Post-It note thing and voting and all
that then I think it was Eli's idea to
ask the second followup question which
was so how many of you are actually
doing these
things and a different set of hands went
up that's an interesting data point and
the list here on the left is organized
by the
Gap uh how many of you think it's
important but aren't doing it and the
first thing on that list was logging
actions on search results the first
thing on the list so as a product
manager I want to listen to people and
say okay sounds like that's important
sounds like people aren't doing it
aren't happy with the way they're doing
it and there are various other things
like understand the application data
we've heard about that here too but you
actually want to know what are the
semantic relations this field that says
company is its standard I ized in some
way is it the same kind of company name
that appears in this other field and so
on so forth that was the second third
was evaluating the quality of the
results which comes back to using this
data and then there are various others
which are also important but not really
the topic
today so that was interesting but of
course you know at brilliant buzzwords
you see a lot of middle-size small
companies amateurs you know people like
you who don't really know what they're
doing I'm sorry
um but I thought well let's look at our
real customers let's look at AWS
customers so I spent quite a while it
took me longer than it should have but I
spent some time talking to our
salespeople and saying I really want to
get into meetings with people who are
using
search and um the reason took me a while
is that they didn't quite understand
that they didn't quite understand the
notion of search as opposed to other
applications of open search they didn't
quite understand that relevance
Engineers are a different population
than operations Engineers so it took a
while to get to the right
people but finally I got to the right
people at various
companies and I sort of discussed with
them well you know what are your
challenges what are you what are you up
to what can you tell me about your
philosophy of search and so on the first
thing I discovered was that actually
very few people think of them themselves
themselves as search relevance Engineers
they think of themselves as software
Engineers say oh this is a problem right
here we are the people who come to this
conference are the people who actually
realize that it's a discipline these are
people who don't realize it's a
discipline so that's a serious problem
but then the second thing I noticed was
they all had problems with logging and I
talked to some very large companies
you'd have heard of them I'm not allowed
to tell you who they are of
course and um some of them would say
well I say well tell me a little bit
about your logging do you log let's say
what PE what people click on say oh yeah
of course we log on uh log what people
click on great do you log what people
don't click
on um we hope
okay so you don't log what people don't
click on um so you do you know what
position people are clicking on well you
know Joe has some prototype code that
that does that but I'm not sure I trust
it okay go to another company and said
do you log things so oh yeah yeah we
have some logging code um now Eric wrote
it a couple years ago and uh it seems to
run fine and it collects the data and so
well what if you want to change it uh or
improve it well Eric left the company
and no one really understands his code
because it's spaghetti
code um but so you know we have a
solution but you know if something
better would come along we'll take it go
to another company so you have a logging
solution say well we have a pretty good
logging solution but it's such a pain
you know we we have to assign someone to
to revise it every time we change this
and such and it's really not our
business to work on logging that's not
where we make our money we make our
money and what ever we do we sell
chocolates or we uh find people jobs or
whatever so there was clearly an
appetite quality evaluation was even
worse by the way so even fewer of these
very large companies that you've heard
of with large search teams didn't know
how to evaluate their
results
shocking um they also didn't know how to
use multiple signals I mean some again
very large companies who say have you
thought of using popularity as a signal
in your ranking you can do that you know
all right but that's again
orthogonal so this is the diagram I like
to put up when I talk to to customers
and even to
you and uh you see on the top left you
have search Pro what I call search
processing these are all the techniques
you use to create search
results and people love to talk about
these techniques people spend lots of
time talking about these techniques te
in fact most of what goes on at this
conference is also about these
techniques are you using Vector search
are you using what sort of tricks are
you doing with lexical search how are
you doing hybridization how are you uh
combining hybrids um you know are you
using sparse neural also called Spade
you know all this stuff people get
really excited about the stuff at the
top left I say that's great then
what do you evaluate the results well
you know who has the time to do
that and again in talking to these very
large customers you say there's a gap
and so we've been thinking a lot about
the top right which is measurement and
one critical component of that it's not
the whole thing but one critical
component of that is getting the raw
data so that's the the problem we've
decided to focus on and then once you
have that you can start working on
tuning you say okay we'll adjust
parameters
whatever so these are the various search
processing algorithms that we all know
about and I don't think I need to go
into too much detail on these uh today
uh oh by the way just um because I'm
such a cranky guy uh I'll say I insist
on lexical search not keyword search
keyword actually means something very
specific and it's not the same thing
damn it
anyway so what is user Behavior insights
it's about recording the endtoend search
behavior in a standard
way and in working with with Eric and
his team we have some principles that we
work on the first principle is that the
most important thing we're doing is
standardizing the schema for the events
that's not even a piece of software just
agreeing on what words mean basically
the second thing we're doing is
collecting providing the software to
collect those events and the third thing
we're doing is helping analyze those
events because once you have the data
you know analysis should come fairly
easily um and there are various ways of
using it of course how to use it you can
tune manually me the the finger
certainly needs some data uh you can do
basian parameter optimization you can
find Jor models but all of these things
depend on having some data on how good
is the result learning to rank of course
and my favorite combining neural and and
Leal uh excuse well that's a typo that's
should be neural and and the vector
rankings um so all of these things
require data to help you you get the
right results so what does Ubi let you
do user Behavior insights well there are
all sorts of applications you can
dashboard and managers love dashboards I
don't find them that useful to tell you
the truth but except when there's a bump
you say oh gee that's funny why why did
that change so suddenly investigation of
particular Problems by relevant
Engineers data scientist collecting
judgment for offline evaluation so even
though we have all this Dynamic data we
do still want to do offline evaluation
so where do you get the queries brought
valuation get them here debugging tuning
of all sorts of Parts type ahead and so
on real-time feedback to relevance
feedback so I'll I'll mention that we're
working with another team at Amazon
called the personalized team which has a
non-op source product so it's a uh
another part of Amazon we're happy to
work with them we're happy to work with
any one of you we want to make sure that
the data we're providing will allow in
session adjustment of results so our
solution is near real
time and of course we all know that you
need this data for as input to machine
learning models that's the sort of
obvious
thing so what's this project well Eric
and I discussed this I think two years
ago at hastac or actually myy at hastac
two years ago and I I button hold and
said Eric why don't we have a standard
way of reporting this data and he said
good
idea said okay um and so we put out an
RFC in in our our GitHub in
2022 we revised it uh this January and
updated again uh just the last
week the community debated names we make
frequent presentations at the open
search Community meetings so this is all
Community feedback based all the work
we're doing all the software all the
discussion is happen well I occasionally
talk to Derek without recording our our
conversation but the discussions happen
on GitHub and all everything we're doing
everything we're delivering is under the
Apache 2
license so now it's Eric's turn to show
what we're actually doing all right so
quick quick change
hopefully we got 19 minutes
all
right here's your phone
stabus and we believe the left side
works better all
right gonna grab this laptop right here
all right we got audio video all right
fantastic so all right yall can hear me
terrific so thank you very much Savas
for kind of setting the the context of
everything
in my notes so uh all right great so uh
yeah so right thank you all right
so really quick right so stabos talked
about how we're getting information
we're looking for Community feedback and
so just five questions right really
simple simple survey we'd love to have
uh some feedback from all of you uh on
on on kind of where you are and we will
post the feedback it's just a couple of
scores uh in the relevance slack hstack
chat so everybody got that if you don't
have it I can get do it later so
obviously this is very personal to me
and so I kind of wanted to share why I'm
excited about Ubi right and why this has
been such a an interesting journey to go
on some of you may have seen this
diagram at other Hast at conferences
it's one I use all the time it's how I
think about um you know relevance
Improvement and you know we got our two
wheels we have our lab offline
environment it moves really fast it
evolves you know we try things out we
you know use this great data um thanks
for the shout out about implicit
judgments and stuff for offline testing
and then we have our live online
environment and it's big it's where we
really validate that our experiments and
ideas are actually what our users agree
with right and what I find is that
there's often a gap right the
clickstream portion of it is a gap and
as a relevance engineer right you know
it's sometimes difficult to work in that
space it's a separate team it's a
separate product you know a lot of the
issues that stabber has kind of
highlighted and I find that without the
without the clickstream being really
robust and really designed for what I
need as a relevance engineer
[Music]
it's to do my job to be effective to run
both sides of the relevancy
framework so I was digging around I
actually found the copy of this slide
from
2021 and 20 or 20 and there's 2020 Eric
saying ug Google analytics that's what I
got that's what I got most of the time
right uh and you know it it it it kind
of sucks so uh I am incredibly excited
about working on opportunity to improve
to fill this Gap in with something that
is meant for
us so there's three parts to this sort
of user Behavior insights project
obviously some code for collecting
specific events right we've all been out
there we've seen the little bit of
JavaScript or something in the middle
tier whatever we have to uh collect some
events and we've really been trying not
to build that ourselves because honestly
everybody's going to want to build their
own anyway uh but we do have sort of a
goal of providing a starter basic
JavaScript client for those uh that
people could use uh but definitely an an
area where there could be some great
contributions from the
community now a big area that we spend a
lot of time on we want a shared schema
right we need a way of defining what the
users are asking for and understanding
what is a query right and you know we're
trying to you know what is the user
query we need to also have a good way of
tracking and articulating back what are
the documents objects records chunks
what are the things that we are
returning back to the user right because
that's that's you know as important um
as understanding what your user queries
are and then of course what we're trying
to do is build a strong I think stabos
likes to use the word causal
relationship a causal connection between
the user did this query they picked
these facets then they did these things
and we want to do a better job of making
that breadcrumb Journey clearer and more
visible than maybe some of the other
tooling that's out there especially the
things that are specific to us in our
industry and then lastly of course right
we're starting out with making an
implementation uh in open search I want
to make a quick shout out to my
colleague Jeff back there raise your
hand who's been leading a lot of that
effort and has been really awesome uh
and yeah really appreciate Jeff so so of
these three things
though one of them is more important
than the other two it's that shared
schema right and this is where we're
really hoping to get a lot more input uh
from the community is is is this a
schema that you could use is this
something that makes sense are we rich
enough in the places we need to be
really rich are we extensible enough in
the places we need to be extensible or
are we too extensible and it's
impossible for you to build a decent
dashboard of
visualization uh uh on top of this and
maybe we need something less extensible
and more structur
right um the value in this project Right
is coming up with a shared schema that
we can all
use so really quickly wanted to throw up
a quick diagram before I do a demo to of
of of what this looks like right not too
surprising right uh you know we start
out and we we we have a query uh you
know you type in something in the search
bar we're sending a query to you know in
our case op search so underscore search
and the other request handlers we're
actually working on componentry in there
to intercept that query and the
documents that going to be respond and
we're actually writing them out to an
index in the background right it creates
a Ubi or UB queries and UB events Index
right there in your open search so just
without doing anything else if you start
using this we're going to start building
a view of when ques happen what
documents are being returned over time
now we're going to return back to the
front end however that looks like a
query ID and the query ID is a unique
indicator right this is the thing that
said that helps us that allows us to tie
together the query to the return
documents and get start building a view
of and then what did the user do what
did they click on what did they not
click on right um that query idea is
sort of the key bit yes it's some state
right it's something we have to manage
in the front end right we we have to
accept that to be successful in this
we're going to have to work with a you
know in the front end we can't do
everything just on the back end so
there's our three results we got three
documents right result a b and c our
user you know clicks on result C that's
the one that is attractive to them right
they like that one we go ahead and we
log that click through back to our UB
index we bring up our detail view we're
still preserving that query ID right
it's sort of the query ID which would
let us understand what facets had they
picked where uh what search query had
they done um all of that sort of uh
state or context for their
search we love result three it's exactly
what we want we're really happy we click
our add to cart same query ID but a new
event getting logged into our back end
right that looks like a positive signal
for whatever that query and set of
documents were and you know
interestingly result three result C
might be a better result than b or a
because the user picked on it clicked
through it and then bought it so just
one slightly different view of the same
thing before everybody said say uh wait
you can't write everything directly to
open search right I think that one of
the interesting things you know we're
looking at you know data prepper is a
endpoint for bringing data in right uh
and you could imagine that we are
gathering our uh events from open
Telemetry que S3 buckets maybe you have
an existing Analytics tool that you
really really like and you're just not
going to change it but if we have the
query ID in there and a couple maybe we
could set that and bring it back into
open search one of the things I'm really
curious about or want to hear is anyone
who is doing sort of in session
personalization where maybe the near
realtime aspect of writing events
directly into our Ubie events directly
without going through sort of a batch or
a queue might actually be useful for the
next query I can inform it by what you
just did or your previous clicks right
be interesting to see that um
so all
right so I'm going to go ahead give a
quick demo hopefully everything bears
with me all
right so some of you all may have seen
this this is chorus it's our reference
implementation for e-commerce search we
have a number of flavors of It Solar
elastic search and now open search uh
and in this particular one I have it um
set up and so you can see there's my
user id my session I'm going to go ahead
and open up the
console and turn off errors warnings see
right and so you know this shouldn't be
a big surprise I clicked in the search
box we're kind of aggressively in this
POC logging everything like every click
and everything this may not actually
despite what stavo said about his
terabytes and pedabytes of data we might
not actually want to log every Mouse
click and everything else it also makes
for a rather jarring experience but you
know there I am
laptop right there I am looking for
laptops and you can see that I've got
some on search events and I'm logging
things uh in the background I have
logged that for this query laptops these
are the doc IDs that we're
returning we're not logging every
document that matched we're just logging
whatever your Row setting are right
because what we really care about is not
every document what we really care about
is documents that users could interact
with right because that's what's really
important we're focused on the query and
what the and the
user and you know if I go in here and
all right you know I'm gonna pick some
HP laptops see what we got
right yeah there should be where's
my okay there we go just took a second
right I can see that and you can see the
events okay makes sense kind of
straightforward right okay all right so
moving on um so where is all this data
going right so we are leveraging our
open search
infrastructure uh so let's go ahead and
just take a you know I'll take a quick
look see at our uh queries index here
and so there you can see the structure
of our queries and let me SC scroll down
that's that's a little bit of a nicer
one right so there you can see that we
have a query ID uh for that user we're
actually currently logging like the raw
query as like what open search is
getting what we've realiz is we actually
really care about what the user typed in
not you know there are other tools that
could do tell us about the expanded
Lucine query uh but you know there we
are we got our query ID and there right
is a list of the documents that are
being returned to the front end okay uh
sort of similar structure for events
right there we go right you can see we
did a product hover what the last query
ID was uh prior to this um we have some
various sort of message and info and you
know uh an event attributes data
structure in here so all right so you
can see it works but how would I use it
so stabos did highlight that one of the
groups that's very interested in this is
the personalized team right and in the
personalized team they need to know a
user they need to know an item they need
to know a timestamp and they need to
have some sense of what like the
interaction was right so let's see if we
can quy
that so here we go right uh so uh right
here so there I go so I've written so go
ahead and grab my ID as the user ID
column that they're looking for there
you can see we're digging into our uh
event attributes and grabbing the object
that we're interacting with right uh and
we're grabbing out the item id obviously
we got our timestamp there um and then
you know our our action name and some
messaging and specifically right the
personalized team at least right now
hasn't said Global hover or every click
they're interested in they're interested
in certain events right and so you know
an add to cart event obviously is
probably a pretty uh strong signal so we
are just filtering it down for a a
specific user just for the purposes of
this demo and then you know what the
action is that we're looking for here we
doing add to
cart go ahead and run
this and there we go and so what's
interesting is if you look at this data
right is this user is clearly interested
in technology products right because
they keep adding them is there anything
else that you might notice about this
user any other preferences that they
might be expressing just by looking at
the types of products that they add to
their cart
HP right thank you thank you very much
Maya right uh she understood the
assignment um so yeah right this is
really interesting right here right I am
seeing that this person has a proclivity
towards HP products they like the
notebooks the parts the desktops you
know not that there aren't other brands
in there but they like the HP products
so potentially an interesting experiment
to do with this data would be to boost
on the HP brand right in subsequent
queries because they clearly uh they
seem to have an affinity okay excellent
uh and my laptop's going to die right
about when I'm supposed to be done okay
so that's great so that's where we are
right
now so the way we're enabling these
queries for those of you who are curious
ah thank you
stabus you're good man
uh is um you know we we've kind of gone
around a couple ways but we're adding a
stanza Ubi uh and there's sort of an
example of what we really care about is
the user query The Wind Rises not the
expanded query that went through the
merchandising layer and you know
exploded it into the query string that
you see there right and so if we see a
Ubi clause in there we enable the Ubi
function Opa
search one of things we've heard from a
couple of people though is a lot of
people are going to want to manage that
query ID right it could be a goid and if
you don't provide one you get a goid but
maybe you want to put some context in
there right um I think this is a point
of debate or question is it a good idea
to embed some context into your
individual query ID and manage it from
outside I I don't know the answer I'd
love to talk more people about it but
there sort of an example we're sending
that in now um on the indexing side um
so the demo I showed you was built with
open search 2.13 came out a couple of
weeks ago and we actually wrote a plugin
for open search and we actually had our
own endpoint on that plugin to receive
events but the feedback we got and
looking at it is everybody is going to
want to manage that event pipeline in
different ways right and so mandating
you must use this one plug-in endpoint I
mean it was nice from the perspective we
could maybe enforce a schema and do some
other things there but it also hurt us
on supporting like scalability and
different approaches so we kind of took
a step back and in the next versions of
open search what we're saying is we're
just going to be another index like all
your other indexes and so going to
piggyback on your indexing pipeline that
you already know and like um you could
post events directly in like I'm showing
here or you can do you know write to an
S3 bucket and use data prepper to suck
it in and then write it so uh so that's
how we're doing it so um I'm going to be
sharing these slides and one of the
things that I want to highlight is we've
written a fair amount of documentation
around the schema because that is the uh
the the the the any bit in this um uh
and so uh yeah all right I got just a
moment to finish this up so I know what
you all are thinking when we talk about
we ought to have a
standard right yeah you're all thinking
this right 14 standards and now we have
15 but what I am suggesting is that at
least in our industry and what we're
doing
this is the actual situation there are
no competing standards right we have
zero competing standards because we
don't have any standards everybody is
separate but maybe if we're successful
on this effort we could have one
cooperating standard going forward so
we'll
see uh there's your QR code to bring up
this page if you want to try out some of
the links the RFC is public we're
looking for comment
uh we've gone through three revisions so
we're looking for
comments but you know productive ones uh
we got some documentation we have the
schema um the demo that I showed uh
that's the repo there it's a Docker
image with a quick start shell script
and of course we have an online demo try
out those links you can bring up exactly
what I just did so uh yeah and so I'm
super excited Ed that at the end of this
journey maybe I can close this ticket to
track clicks using a generalizable
signals format thank
you I don't know that we have qu time
for questions Scott or
all right oh excellent so in terms of
data collection have you devised a loose
coupling for endpoint data ingestion
into pipeline right airflow kfka Etc one
of the I think that the answer is that's
why we're not doing our own plug-in with
our own data collection endpoint and
just being plain old open search right
because everybody's going to want to do
that differently we're going to be
demoing it with data prepper right we're
going to demo it with some JavaScript
that people can use right but people who
are like we use these Technologies we
should be able to adapt to that very
quickly right
so who's managing the question are you
managing the question
yeah up
there forming aggregations rankings
comparisons summ ation across multiple
objects um so I think there's two way
that things go one is tangent to AB
testing in a variety of ways there's
also latent s signals that come out of
AB testing like how long your users sit
on a page before they do an action right
uh that seems like they should also be
included in this well every everything
is time stamped so all the actions are
time stamped so latency is cly something
you can measure right and then the other
bits and pieces of this are when dealing
with personalization at least in in the
company I work for that's very difficult
because Google's really effectively
trained our users if they don't see the
first two results what they want then
they'll put in another query another
query and another query so unless you
can
apply that result to analyze the queries
fast enough to do the personalization
it's it's hard this this seems like a uh
would work really well when you have uh
users that are well trained to look at a
bunch of stuff yeah and so maybe it
would be nice to think about uh a small
result set version right yeah no I love
that idea I mean I'm I'm super intrigued
by the in session personalization I'll
admit it's a little out of the scope of
what we're trying to build here it's I
think a great use case and one I'd love
to hear more about uh because of exactly
those challenges right yeah for for now
we're looking at like seconds of latency
is not enough to handle the rapid fire
queries uh we do hope that we'll get it
down to know under a second but that's
aspiration yeah all you want to get
another question while I try
find hey thanks so much for your talk um
I'm GNA be it's the best one I've been
to In This section so uh I work I'm a
data scientist I work on the search team
at Reddit um I just want to confirm that
this is a great track and I can't wait
to look into it as well we went through
with similar Journey inhouse probably
about two years ago and we ended up with
a lot of similar Concepts and constructs
that yall did and from the cooperating
standard I believe a great route would
and you're probably heading this way but
the schema essentially what I would call
like the core schema and then any
implementers can have their own
secondary schema that would have domain
specific aspects as well that's exactly
what we have so so we have the course
schema which basically you're saying we
recommend that you report at least these
things yeah which lets you do these
kinds of analysis that's right beyond
that we have optional things and our
goal is to Define all of these fields in
such a way that if it's a well- defined
field you know what you should put into
it right uh it's not required nothing's
required but you should at least know
what goes in there and if you have a
user ID you know what a user ID is and
the notion of a user ID is simply a
unique ID even if it has internal
structure the internal structure isn't
our business y great I like to that I'll
follow with you all personally so I'd
love to have your feedback uh on on site
about since you have the experience with
the with the S of thing at
Reddit all right thank you Eric thank
you stavos we have a
r thank
you all right we have another 15 minutes
before our next talk okay you Scott
bringing us home right yeah yeah C up
better all